<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Petko's Coding Blog - Machine Learning</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/feeds/machine-learning.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://pminkov.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2012-07-29T22:33:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Plotting in Octave.</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/plotting-in-octave.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-29T22:33:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-07-29T22:33:00-07:00</updated><author><name>softwarecomments</name></author><id>tag:pminkov.github.io,2012-07-29:/blog/plotting-in-octave.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Plotting functions in Octave is quite easy and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
In the lecture on neural networks from Stanford's
&lt;a href="http://ml-class.org/"&gt;machine learning class&lt;/a&gt; a function related to neural
networks is introduced. The function has two inputs - x1 and x2 and it's
supposed to model a logical AND operation. The function is based on …</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Plotting functions in Octave is quite easy and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
In the lecture on neural networks from Stanford's
&lt;a href="http://ml-class.org/"&gt;machine learning class&lt;/a&gt; a function related to neural
networks is introduced. The function has two inputs - x1 and x2 and it's
supposed to model a logical AND operation. The function is based on the
sigmoid function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The sigmoid function looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt="Google sigmoid plot" src="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/images/sigmoid-google.png"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Computing the sigmoid function in Octave can be seen
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/3205075" title="Sidmoid"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The given example plugs x1 and x2 into the sigmoid function by
computing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
f(x1, x2) = sigmoid(-30 + 20*x1 + 20*x2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
f(1, 1) evaluates to 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
f(0, 0), f(0, 1) and f(1, 0) evaluate to 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Intuitively that make sense. Even if x1 or x2 is 1, -30 + 20 is -10,
which corresponds to a very low value for the sigmoid function, as you
can see from the graph above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
I got curious about how this function looks like for values between zero
and one and wrote this &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/3205016"&gt;short Octave
program&lt;/a&gt; to plot the output. And here
it is. Pretty neat, I'd say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img alt="Octave sigmoid plot" src="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/images/sigmoid-octave.png"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
It's easy to see that the function behaves as expected at (0,0), (0,1)
and (1,0) and (1,1) and that for values in between its computed values
are somewhere in between as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Machine Learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Stanford's machine learning class.</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/stanfords-machine-learning-class.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-07-27T15:00:45-07:00</published><updated>2012-07-27T15:00:45-07:00</updated><author><name>Petko Minkov</name></author><id>tag:pminkov.github.io,2012-07-27:/blog/stanfords-machine-learning-class.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stanford's machine learning class on coursera is pretty good. What's
surprising to me is that exercises take much more time than listening to
lectures and taking after class quizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The programming environment used for the class is Octave. The most
challenging part so far with writing code in Octave is …</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Stanford's machine learning class on coursera is pretty good. What's
surprising to me is that exercises take much more time than listening to
lectures and taking after class quizes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The programming environment used for the class is Octave. The most
challenging part so far with writing code in Octave is coming up with
what's called vectorization solutions. The idea of vectorization is that
instead of writing loops, you compute values by vector and matrix
operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Let's look at a simple example. Imagine that you have a vector of zeros
and ones. You have to convert it to a vector where for each one we have
a one and for each zero we have minus one. That came up as a component
of the cost function computation in logistic regression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
An iterative solution in Scala might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
v.map(x =&amp;gt; if (x == 0) -1 else 1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
How would that look in Octave if we can't use loops and if statements? A
function F that maps from {0, 1} to {-1, 1} actually looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
F(x) = 2x - 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Pretty cool. Now if our vector of zeros and ones is A, by using that
function, we can compute the desired value by doing this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
D = 2 * A - 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
This is pretty much only a part of a typical vectorized computation in
machine learning. Crafting those takes some time, but at the end there's
a good a-ha moment and usually a quite short solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
So far I went through the linear and logistic regression lectures. Both
methods are widely practical and it's very easy to come up with usage
example. Those methods are examples of supervised learning algorithms,
since we train them on a data set and then once we've computed a model
we just plug new examples into it and come up with results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
In practice, I doubt that anyone is going to implement their own
gradient descent algorithms to come up with model coefficients. I'd
expect that usually a library / package like Matlab / Octave / R will be
used to train a model. Implementing the model itself is quite trivial
and would be just a couple of lines of code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Machine Learning"></category></entry></feed>