<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Petko's Coding Blog - Misc</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://pminkov.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2017-04-24T21:10:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Visualizing algorithms with Jupyter notebooks</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/visualizing-algorithms-with-jupyter-notebooks.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-04-24T21:10:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-04-24T21:10:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Petko Minkov</name></author><id>tag:pminkov.github.io,2017-04-24:/blog/visualizing-algorithms-with-jupyter-notebooks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last couple of days I was looking into some old implementation of k-means clustering that I wrote. At that time I didn't know how to use matplotlib and to display the clusters that were generated and I was printing commands that I was plugging into R. Since then, I've learned …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last couple of days I was looking into some old implementation of k-means clustering that I wrote. At that time I didn't know how to use matplotlib and to display the clusters that were generated and I was printing commands that I was plugging into R. Since then, I've learned how to use Jupyter, so I sat down and imported the code into a Jupyter notebook that's visualizing the algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the &lt;a href="http://nbviewer.jupyter.org/github/pminkov/notebooks/blob/master/k-means%20clustering.ipynb"&gt;Jupyter notebook&lt;/a&gt;. Overall, I quite enjoy how this format mixes the results of code execution with Markdown segments.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Thoughts on C programming.</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/thoughts-on-c-programming.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-01T17:58:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-01-01T17:58:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Petko Minkov</name></author><id>tag:pminkov.github.io,2017-01-01:/blog/thoughts-on-c-programming.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a &lt;a href="https://github.com/pminkov/webserver"&gt;webserver&lt;/a&gt; in C and wanted to share my thoughts on writing code in C. This was practically my first somewhat substantial C project. I've had two jobs in which I was writing C++, but I never programmed in C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in no particular order, here are …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently wrote a &lt;a href="https://github.com/pminkov/webserver"&gt;webserver&lt;/a&gt; in C and wanted to share my thoughts on writing code in C. This was practically my first somewhat substantial C project. I've had two jobs in which I was writing C++, but I never programmed in C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in no particular order, here are my thoughts on C.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-language-is-simple"&gt;The language is simple.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C is a pretty simple language. Unlike complicated languages like Scala, C has a very limited set of language features. There's a good side to that - you can start faster with C and I appreciate the simplicity coming from working with a more limited language. On the other hand, you have to write more code to do certain things.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="lack-of-object-oriented-programming-makes-writing-code-more-difficult"&gt;Lack of object oriented programming makes writing code more difficult.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's difficult to organize code when you don't have classes. It seems like your option is to just put pieces of code in separate files if you want to do that. But then, function names will still have to be different. So you end up with a lot of functions containing the name of the type they're supposed to operate on, like maybe &lt;code&gt;add_to_tree&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code&gt;remove_from_tree&lt;/code&gt; instead of simple &lt;code&gt;add&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;remove&lt;/code&gt; methods on a &lt;code&gt;Tree&lt;/code&gt; class.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="not-knowing-the-size-of-arrays-and-strings-in-advance-is-difficult"&gt;Not knowing the size of arrays and strings in advance is difficult.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike C++, C doesn't have its STL library, so if you're allocating arrays or strings, you often have to know their size in advance. Imagine running a process with &lt;code&gt;popen&lt;/code&gt; and having to store its output to a string. You can't know the size of the output in advance, so you have to allocate a buffer of a certain size, expecting it to be big enough in all cases. That's of course impossible, so you'll need to code your own variable size string.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C library functions are also not immune to this problem. For example, the &lt;code&gt;getcwd&lt;/code&gt; is a function that gets the current working directory. It receives a buffer of a certain size and writes the directory name to it. If the buffer is smaller than the directory name, the function will return NULL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, in a lot of cases, you'd know the size of the data in advance, but writing code that has to do with strings and arrays is still more difficult than just using a STL &lt;code&gt;vector&lt;/code&gt; or a &lt;code&gt;stack&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="you-have-to-be-meticulous-in-checking-return-codes-of-standard-library-functions"&gt;You have to be meticulous in checking return codes of standard library functions.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the functions in the C standard library return something that indicates the success or failure of the function. Unlike languages that have exceptions, if you don't check the return values, it's entirely possible that your code will continue to execute and ignore some errors. Since often times you'll find yourself thinking "I doubt this can fail", writing good C code requires an extra level of discipline.&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Scala scopes.</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/scala-scopes.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-04-27T23:26:00-07:00</published><updated>2012-04-27T23:26:00-07:00</updated><author><name>softwarecomments</name></author><id>tag:pminkov.github.io,2012-04-27:/blog/scala-scopes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;After some programming with Scala, there are a couple of language
features which I really like. One of them is scopes that can evaluate to
a value. How does that look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/2516506.js" type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;![CDATA[// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&gt;]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Ignore the obvious inefficiencies …</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After some programming with Scala, there are a couple of language
features which I really like. One of them is scopes that can evaluate to
a value. How does that look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/2516506.js" type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;![CDATA[// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]&gt;&lt;![CDATA[&gt;]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Ignore the obvious inefficiencies of the code and take a look at how you
can put a block of code inside the inner scope. What's good about that?
This inner scope is like a lighweight function. The benefits are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variables in the function are not seen outside of the scope. Great,
    because you'll get a compile error if you try to use one of
    those variables. Once you're working in the scope you know that any
    variable you declare inside of it won't be used on the outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have a logical block of computation that has a clear start and
    finish, which makes the code easier to read and work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike a function, you don't need to declare function parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drawback is of course that this can become an excuse for creating
long functions, with a lot of scopes like this one inside of them. If
that's avoided, this language feature leads to easier to understand
code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Fun problem with Scala.</title><link href="http://pminkov.github.io/blog/fun-problem-with-scala.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2012-03-06T23:28:00-08:00</published><updated>2012-03-06T23:28:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Petko Minkov</name></author><id>tag:pminkov.github.io,2012-03-06:/blog/fun-problem-with-scala.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a fun problem to solve with Scala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Given N lists, dedupe them with the following rules. Go through the
first list, dedupe it. Go through every consecutive list and only leave
items which are not in a previous list and also take care of removing
duplicates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The challenge here …</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a fun problem to solve with Scala.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
Given N lists, dedupe them with the following rules. Go through the
first list, dedupe it. Go through every consecutive list and only leave
items which are not in a previous list and also take care of removing
duplicates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The challenge here is to do this without using vars and by only using
vals. If you use vars, the solution is trivial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
The solution to this problem is using foldLeft. foldLeft essentially
gives you a way to operate on the elements of a list while aggregating
some state. The state you aggregate is the elements you've already seen
and the current result. The final solution looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/1991619.js" type="text/javascript"&gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;]]&amp;gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
And while we're at it, let's see how the C++ solution looks like, for
comparison. My C++ might be a bit rusty, but the result is longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;script src="https://gist.github.com/1991674.js" type="text/javascript"&gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// &amp;lt;![CDATA[&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;// ]]]]&amp;gt;&amp;lt;![CDATA[&amp;gt;]]&amp;gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>